<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>James Ravindran - long form</title>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.jamesravindran.com/tags/long-form/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.jamesravindran.com"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2021-09-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.jamesravindran.com/tags/long-form/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>An in-depth look into Android vs. iOS, in terms of security and freedom</title>
        <published>2021-09-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2021-09-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.jamesravindran.com/blog/in-depth-look-ios-vs-android/"/>
        <id>https://www.jamesravindran.com/blog/in-depth-look-ios-vs-android/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://www.jamesravindran.com/blog/in-depth-look-ios-vs-android/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;iphone-android-chess-battle.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The battle of the duopoly&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-0-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-0&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, in this post I’m going to dive into the whole rabbit hole of benefits and problems surrounding the two dominant players in smartphones today - &lt;strong&gt;Android and iOS&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; - and whether there are any solutions in sight. We’re going over this with a very fine comb, so be prepared to brace yourself - &lt;strong&gt;if you’re running short of time, don’t worry&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, I’ve put an (admittedly vague) &lt;strong&gt;conclusion at the end&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, but as you are about to see (as with many things), &lt;strong&gt;neither is perfect.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As a disclaimer before we start&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; - due to my perhaps soft heart for open source (although I’d think you would agree is definitely beneficial for all), &lt;strong&gt;I do lean towards Android, but the irony is that I still begrudgingly use iOS devices&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; - you’ll probably see why but I’ll explain at the end anyway.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;ios&quot;&gt;iOS&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with iOS. To give credit to Apple, because they control all the hardware and software, they &lt;strong&gt;will keep providing all security patches for your device&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; - but &lt;strong&gt;only if you are running the latest major iOS version&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. If you are not, you don’t need to worry too much, but &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apple.stackexchange.com&#x2F;questions&#x2F;223170&#x2F;what-is-apples-policy-for-supporting-security-updates-on-older-versions-of-ios&quot;&gt;Apple &lt;strong&gt;will only provide updates for severe vulnerabilities&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (such as against exploits in Safari) for iOS versions near to the latest one. In a sense, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;security.stackexchange.com&#x2F;questions&#x2F;135781&#x2F;does-apple-backport-fixes&quot;&gt;you might be more vulnerable if you are on much lower iOS versions&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (as Apple probably will presume most people will use the latest version for their device and not care to backport fixes too far) but &lt;strong&gt;upgrading might &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;LegacyJailbreak&#x2F;comments&#x2F;li4te8&#x2F;question_should_i_downgrade_ipad_3_from_935_to_841&#x2F;gn15brz&quot;&gt;cause you to lose performance and more “stronger” jailbreaks&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (such as those that use untethered exploits)&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-1-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-1&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this control, although opinions may vary on this, comes at a cost in freedom. &lt;strong&gt;Non-jailbroken iPhones can only download software from Apple’s curated App Store&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; - a “walled garden” in a sense (there’s &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;explainlikeimfive&#x2F;comments&#x2F;9qsbo8&#x2F;eli5_what_is_a_wall_garden&#x2F;e8blw0y&quot;&gt;a nice explanation applying this analogy on Reddit&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;). Of course, the reasoning for this is so Apple can check apps are safe before offering them to users (instead of checking them yourself as on Windows or Android&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-2-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-2&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;), and although the App Store does contain quite a lot of software, there is &lt;strong&gt;a perception that Apple uses this in an additional way to reject apps that they don’t like.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; For instance, &lt;strong&gt;you cannot easily get software like emulators on iOS&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (on Android, you can simply sideload them, but &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;play.google.com&#x2F;store&#x2F;apps&#x2F;details?id=com.retroarch&quot;&gt;Google seemingly does allow them on its Play Store, such as RetroArch&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;). Apple has faced criticism over its treatment of third-party developers from companies such as &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.gamasutra.com&#x2F;view&#x2F;news&#x2F;318850&#x2F;Valves_Steam_Link_app_blocked_by_Apple_due_to_business_conflicts.php&quot;&gt;Valve&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.hey.com&#x2F;apple&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Basecamp&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.theverge.com&#x2F;22611236&#x2F;epic-v-apple-emails-project-liberty-app-store-schiller-sweeney-cook-jobs&quot;&gt;most famously Epic Games whose lawsuit brought a massive amount of revelations&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, shedding light on Apple and even other notable companies in the technology and game industries as a whole.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube-nocookie.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;euiSHuaw6Q4&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Epic parodied &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;1984_(advertisement)&quot;&gt;Apple&#x27;s famous 1984 advert&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; as it filed its lawsuit, alleging Apple holds a monopolistic position over its App Store.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-20-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-20&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d also point out that unlike Android&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-3-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-3&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;you cannot use custom ROMs or other operating systems on iOS devices.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; This is because Apple employs &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;support.apple.com&#x2F;en-gb&#x2F;guide&#x2F;security&#x2F;secb3000f149&#x2F;web&quot;&gt;a chain of trust&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; as a security measure during booting&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; that ensures each successive stage that runs is signed only by them.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-4-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-4&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; The very first stage is &lt;strong&gt;written directly to the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.theiphonewiki.com&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Bootrom&quot;&gt;ROM chip (Bootrom)&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, so it cannot be modified.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-5-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-5&quot;&gt;[7]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; In theory, you could &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;wiki.postmarketos.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Apple_iPhone_7&#x2F;7%2B_(apple-iphone7)&quot;&gt;boot another OS using a semi-tethered exploit&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; such as &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;checkra.in&#x2F;&quot;&gt;checkra1n&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (but as the name implies, you need to have the iPhone connected to a computer to exploit it while it is booting, which is quite inconvenient). &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-6-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-6&quot;&gt;[8]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-7-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-7&quot;&gt;[9]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response to iOS’s walled garden, a lot of users “break out of this jail” using community-developed &lt;strong&gt;jailbreak&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; exploits. &lt;strong&gt;Jailbreaking is &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Jailbreaking_(iOS)#United_States&quot;&gt;certainly legal, at least in the US&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;,&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-8-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-8&quot;&gt;[10]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;support.apple.com&#x2F;en-gb&#x2F;HT201954&quot;&gt;despite Apple’s resentment to jailbreaking&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (and continuous cat-and-mouse patching with each new version) and it does allow you to have more freedom and control over your device like those who use Android.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some, like Apple, that say jailbreaking is a potential security risk, and while I do agree that &lt;strong&gt;if you remain on lower iOS versions&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-9-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-9&quot;&gt;[11]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;, you might be more susceptible to vulnerabilities that would have been patched&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (although there wouldn’t be that many), and perhaps there is &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;jailbreak&#x2F;comments&#x2F;8wu4q9&#x2F;discussion_can_we_speak_about_people_who_are&#x2F;&quot;&gt;some debate over the quality of some jailbreak exploits&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (although to be honest I don’t think they would weaken the device to remote exploits at all, and jailbreak authors are simply trying their best to get around iOS’s security measures), it seems the risk of jailbreaking only simply allows the user to install untrusted software, and that &lt;strong&gt;in itself isn’t really an issue with jailbreaking&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; but more &lt;strong&gt;on the user to be wary of what they install&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (especially from piracy or “cracked” repositories), just like on Windows and Android.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s also prudent to acknowledge &lt;strong&gt;government-backed tools such as the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Pegasus_(spyware)&quot;&gt;Pegasus spyware&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, which has been receiving &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Pegasus_Project_(investigation)&quot;&gt;considerable press coverage recently&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-10-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-10&quot;&gt;[12]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; iOS is closed source, which means third-party researchers find it harder to find and report security issues. Google’s Project Zero has &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;9to5google.com&#x2F;2020&#x2F;07&#x2F;22&#x2F;google-project-zero-ios-srd&#x2F;&quot;&gt;criticised Apple for being less accommodating to researchers&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;googleprojectzero.blogspot.com&#x2F;2019&#x2F;08&#x2F;a-very-deep-dive-into-ios-exploit.html&quot;&gt;lax on iOS security&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; in general. It’s debatable, but it is concerning that &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;googleprojectzero.blogspot.com&#x2F;2021&#x2F;01&#x2F;a-look-at-imessage-in-ios-14.html&quot;&gt;Apple’s BlastDoor service in iOS 14&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, designed to protect against the zero-day iMessage exploits Pegasus was using in iOS 13, &lt;strong&gt;clearly &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;billmarczak&#x2F;status&#x2F;1416801637104902146&quot;&gt;isn’t working since Pegasus can still infect a fully updated iPhone on iOS 14.6&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Then again, given the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;OutOfTheLoop&#x2F;comments&#x2F;opzpd2&#x2F;what_is_going_on_with_pegasus_project&#x2F;h6a9ssz&#x2F;&quot;&gt;difficulty and cost of finding or obtaining these zero-day exploits&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, it’s probably not a concern for the average user. But in the end, such incidents are leading to a general shift in opinion: that &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.wired.com&#x2F;story&#x2F;android-zero-day-more-than-ios-zerodium&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Android may actually be slightly more secure than iOS&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (although you&#x27;ll see the catch with this later)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;android&quot;&gt;Android&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Android, on the other hand, is &lt;strong&gt;much more open&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;source.android.com&#x2F;setup&#x2F;start&#x2F;licenses&quot;&gt;Android itself is an &lt;strong&gt;open-source project&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; licensed under the permissive Apache License, and is bundled with the Linux kernel where Google’s patches to it are under GPL&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-11-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-11&quot;&gt;[13]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; This means that anyone, particularly those in the cybersecurity industry, can &lt;strong&gt;readily look and examine the code for security issues and other problems&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;even contribute to Android themselves&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-12-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-12&quot;&gt;[14]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A lot of people consider Android to be insecure, but this seems to be a common misconception.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Android, unlike iOS, simply allows you to download and install (“sideload”) random apps from anywhere (once you’ve enabled a setting at first usually). Admittedly, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.zdnet.com&#x2F;article&#x2F;malicious-apps-on-google-play-dropped-banking-trojans-on-user-devices&#x2F;&quot;&gt;some malicious apps have been found on Google’s Play Store&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, but even Google can’t validate them all (&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;XcodeGhost&quot;&gt;as can’t Apple&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;), &lt;strong&gt;the user should probably treat less known applications with caution before installing them&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (as on Windows and other platforms), sandboxing measures in both iOS and Android should reduce the impact (though as we’ve seen with Pegasus and self-root&#x2F;semi-untethered jailbreaking apps, these can be bypassed through vulnerabilities), and &lt;strong&gt;both iOS and Android have measures to monitor and remotely remove malware from your phone&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; - as seen with &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;android-developers.googleblog.com&#x2F;2017&#x2F;04&#x2F;an-investigation-of-chrysaor-malware-on.html&quot;&gt;Google doing so with the Pegasus version on Android which they nicknamed “Chrysaor”&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-13-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-13&quot;&gt;[15]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a more open platform brings many other benefits as well, which I’ll list here in comparison to iOS:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Developers can make apps on Windows, Linux and MacOS for Android&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; using &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;developer.android.com&#x2F;studio&quot;&gt;Android Studio&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;For iOS, you can only officially make apps on MacOS&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; since &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;developer.apple.com&#x2F;xcode&#x2F;&quot;&gt;XCode&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is only available there. There might be ways to make iOS apps using &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;iphonedev.wiki&#x2F;index.php&#x2F;Theos&quot;&gt;the community SDK for jailbreaking called Theos&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, but I’m doubtful Apple will allow them into its official App Store if they are aware they’ve been made using it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Developers can freely distribute apps on Android outside of the Play Store&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, and if they want to release it on the Play Store anyway, it’s only &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.androidauthority.com&#x2F;publishing-first-app-play-store-need-know-383572&#x2F;&quot;&gt;a one-time fee of $25&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (for iOS, to release an app on the App Store you &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;developer.apple.com&#x2F;programs&#x2F;how-it-works&#x2F;&quot;&gt;must pay &lt;strong&gt;a $99 subscription per year&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, and you &lt;strong&gt;officially sign the app on a Mac&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;stackoverflow.com&#x2F;questions&#x2F;18739387&#x2F;build-an-ios-app-without-owning-a-mac&quot;&gt;although there are ways around that apparently&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;). This is probably fine for most businesses who can afford it, but for open-source developers - such as the ones who made &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;irc&#x2F;comments&#x2F;d3y75s&#x2F;are_there_any_free_open_source_irc_clients_for_ios&#x2F;f05ybf7&quot;&gt;the IRC client Mutter, which ceased development a while ago for presumably this reason&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; - and hobbyists it’s very cost prohibitive, and it’s why most iOS apps are more likely to be paid apps, or utilise in-app purchases and adverts. That’s why &lt;strong&gt;on Android you readily get lots more cool stuff&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; such as from &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.f-droid.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;F-Droid&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, a large collection of &lt;strong&gt;free and open-source applications&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that are safe&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-14-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-14&quot;&gt;[16]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; and warn you of issues such as privacy before installing them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Android, &lt;strong&gt;apparently you can install third-party applications to better secure your phone&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (of course, in a sandbox &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.howtogeek.com&#x2F;232436&#x2F;android-has-a-big-security-problem-but-antivirus-apps-cant-do-much&#x2F;&quot;&gt;these antivirus apps are utterly useless. Don’t really buy into them&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, especially more on iOS, but in general they are quite ineffective - and, in the end, it’s more effective to be careful what you install in the first place). &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.forbes.com&#x2F;sites&#x2F;zakdoffman&#x2F;2021&#x2F;03&#x2F;16&#x2F;iphone-12-pro-max-and-iphone-13-not-more-secure-than-google-and-samsung-android-warns-cyber-billionaire&#x2F;&quot;&gt;I speak more for &lt;strong&gt;professional solutions that will probably affect the phone on the OS level&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; such as those that run as root or patch the phone directly. Although I haven’t used them myself (so I can only speculate), it seems it would be &lt;strong&gt;way easier on Android than iOS&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; to do this sort of thing due to &lt;strong&gt;Android’s open nature&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;With iOS you are more 100% reliant on Apple to secure your phone&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (and with things like Pegasus this can be a concern).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally I should mention (although you can probably guess), &lt;strong&gt;Google happily gives the code away to all kinds of manufacturers such as Samsung, OnePlus, Sony etc.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; to use as long as they are part of &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Open_Handset_Alliance&quot;&gt;Google’s Open Handset Alliance&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (and even those who don’t want to join, such as Amazon, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Fire_OS&quot;&gt;can still use Android due to its open-source license for their devices&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, you’re probably wondering, what’s the catch? &lt;strong&gt;Fragmentation is the catch, my friend.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;android-fragmentation-everywhere.png&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I would like to emphasise, &lt;strong&gt;fragmentation is not inherently a bad thing&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. The wide variety of Android devices is really &lt;strong&gt;a strength of the ecosystem that gives users more choice&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. The &lt;strong&gt;ability for different companies to produce phones&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; offers opportunities to them to &lt;strong&gt;produce innovative features and differentiate their brands&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (which would be more sluggishly adopted by Apple&#x27;s more consistent but concentrated and monolithic approach due to them being heavily vertically integrated).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In comparison to Android, &lt;strong&gt;Microsoft has somehow handled fragmentation incredibly well over the several decade long PC market&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-22-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-22&quot;&gt;[17]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; such that we&#x27;ve managed to get a single operating system to boot across &lt;strong&gt;thousands of variations of hardware&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; thanks to &lt;strong&gt;a standardised BIOS&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. Unfortunately, &lt;strong&gt;that doesn’t exist on ARM&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-23-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-23&quot;&gt;[18]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. Fragmentation is probably the reason that &lt;strong&gt;Android is the most installed OS of all time&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, but the way fragmentation is handled in Android does lead to severe problems with updates (more importantly security ones).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, for Android, &lt;strong&gt;Google hands the code through &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.xda-developers.com&#x2F;googles-project-treble-modularize-android-so-oems-can-update-devices-faster&#x2F;&quot;&gt;like 5 different companies&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; who all modify it so it runs on the final device. So, essentially, &lt;strong&gt;there’s probably hundreds if not thousands of forks of Linux&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (with proprietary binary drivers etc.) &lt;strong&gt;for each individual Android device&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. Passing through updates, such as security ones, through that chain will be slow, and worst of all, when one of those companies decides it is no longer financially viable to support your device, &lt;strong&gt;updates will completely stop&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. There’s an estimated one billion Android devices, vulnerable to publicly known exploits such as &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;KRACK&quot;&gt;KRACK&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Dirty_COW&quot;&gt;Dirty COW&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Stagefright_(bug)&quot;&gt;Stagefright&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (and almost certainly dozens of vulnerabilities in default web browsers on the device and other programs). I mean, in theory, if you’re extremely careful, you might be okay, but it’s like walking on eggshells, and it’s much better if you get a new phone immediately.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-15-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-15&quot;&gt;[19]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google is &lt;strong&gt;trying to improve the situation with things like &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;source.android.com&#x2F;devices&#x2F;architecture#hidl&quot;&gt;Project Treble&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, although &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;postmarketos.org&#x2F;faq&#x2F;#can-project-treble-help-postmarketos&quot;&gt;some do criticise&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;ollieparanoid.github.io&#x2F;post&#x2F;security-warning&#x2F;#outdated-firmware-threatens-old-smartphones&quot;&gt;the kernel and firmware do not receive any further updates&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, and that older devices (unless supported by the community) never get the chance to experience Project Treble. Still, it is bringing out &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.androidcentral.com&#x2F;project-treble-working-even-if-android-updates-dont-all-come-day-one&quot;&gt;faster updates for certain phones&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (for at least the OS component) and now has brought &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;phhusson&#x2F;treble_experimentations&#x2F;wiki&quot;&gt;generic custom ROMs&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that work with many devices, which is nice.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;linux-on-smartphones&quot;&gt;Linux on smartphones?&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To note, &lt;strong&gt;Android phones do have the ability to use custom ROMs&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; like &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;lineageos.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;LineageOS&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (it depends on the phone in general, although &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;fossdroid&#x2F;comments&#x2F;ewd3rs&#x2F;the_best_custom_rom_supported_phone&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Google and OnePlus phones tend to have the best support&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; apparently), but the ideal solution for supporting running Linux would be if all Android OEMs&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-16-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-16&quot;&gt;[20]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; release the source code for the drivers on their phones,&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-17-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-17&quot;&gt;[21]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; but of course all(?) of them do not.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-18-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-18&quot;&gt;[22]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; The good news is that there is &lt;strong&gt;a community project called &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;postmarketos.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;postmarketOS&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; which is seeking to bring mainline Linux to old devices and therefore fix the Android longevity problem, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;cascardo.eti.br&#x2F;blog&#x2F;GNU_on_Smartphones_part_II&#x2F;&quot;&gt;among others&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, to be honest, I don’t mind sacrificing the higher quality (although it is subjective) that comes with iOS or Android for the true Linux freedom on a device - the only issue is that &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;wiki.postmarketos.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Devices&quot;&gt;support for phone by phone varies&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, and even the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;PinePhone&quot;&gt;PinePhone&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; which is made to support mainline Linux &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;PINE64official&#x2F;comments&#x2F;m9kc82&#x2F;is_the_pinephone_a_suitable_daily_driver_yet&#x2F;grnzaxc&quot;&gt;isn’t up to the reliability of Android and iOS phones&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; I’m not sure if it is down to either the hardware (as &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;PINE64official&#x2F;comments&#x2F;njjdfb&#x2F;considering_of_buying_pine64_phone&#x2F;gz7v296&quot;&gt;this Reddit comment&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;PINE64official&#x2F;comments&#x2F;n5xrwk&#x2F;pinephone_thoughts&#x2F;gx3ymhq&quot;&gt;this other Reddit comment&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; seem to imply) or the software (&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;boilingsteam.com&#x2F;the-pinephone-can-it-replace-your-smartphone&#x2F;&quot;&gt;as this review seems to suggest&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;). Nonetheless, &lt;strong&gt;it is very encouraging to see a community who is aware of the issues that face iOS and Android today trying to provide the ideal solution.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion-tl-dr&quot;&gt;Conclusion (tl;dr)&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, though, then again it is up to you. It seems possible that &lt;strong&gt;Android is slightly more secure (and certainly more open) than iOS&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; due to the former’s open source nature, but sadly, &lt;strong&gt;much of this is negated by the poorer flow of updates received on most Android phones&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. It’s exactly why I use iOS&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-21-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-21&quot;&gt;[23]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;, because despite where I look, it seems unfortunate that Android phones (&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;Android&#x2F;comments&#x2F;grlik7&#x2F;two_years_of_software_updates_is_no_longer_enough&#x2F;&quot;&gt;even those reaching $1,000&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;support.google.com&#x2F;pixelphone&#x2F;answer&#x2F;4457705&quot;&gt;those being supported by Google directly&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;) only get at least two years in updates, which pales in comparison to iOS devices reaching around six years (such as those released in around 2015&#x2F;2016 still receiving updates today).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want something usable and reliable (more importantly, in calling and texting) at the present, you’ll have to pick between &lt;strong&gt;iOS (less freedom&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-19-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-19&quot;&gt;[24]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; and more expensive but with longer update support)&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;Android (more freedom and cheaper but with shorter update support).&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Linux-based community efforts are encouraging, but they are not usable yet as a daily driver for most people (but hopefully they will be one day).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-0&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.flickr.com&#x2F;photos&#x2F;nrkbeta&#x2F;3905907831&quot;&gt;&quot;iPhone vs Android&quot;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; by NRKbeta &#x2F; Marius Arnesen (licensed under &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;creativecommons.org&#x2F;licenses&#x2F;by-sa&#x2F;3.0&#x2F;no&#x2F;&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 3.0 NO&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;) &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-0-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the way, if you did want to downgrade your old iOS device for jailbreaking purposes, there is &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;LukeZGD&#x2F;iOS-OTA-Downgrader&quot;&gt;a tool on GitHub to do so&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-1-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On how to actually check them yourself, I’ll probably write another post about that - but basically, you can use websites such as &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.virustotal.com&quot;&gt;VirusTotal&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Note they’re not perfect - they might give false positives, or &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.howtogeek.com&#x2F;howto&#x2F;30508&#x2F;make-sure-downloads-are-safe-before-downloading-them&#x2F;&quot;&gt;sometimes even give a clean result even if what you’re scanning is malware&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, but it’s a good rule of thumb anyway. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-2-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-20&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This whole battle of the Tims (lol) is kind of dripping in irony. Arguably, this video is a clever move by Epic, as it &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.polygon.com&#x2F;2020&#x2F;8&#x2F;13&#x2F;21367803&#x2F;fortnite-1984-apple-app-store-epic-lawsuit-commercial-short-video&quot;&gt;reframes Apple into the position it believed IBM were in 1984&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. And in some &quot;ironyception&quot;, the trial&#x27;s ruling (on page 23) reveals Epic planned to push this as part of a &quot;pre-planned, and blistering, marketing campaign&quot; that would convince the public that they were &quot;benevolent&quot; and that &quot;at the same time make Apple out to be the bad guys&quot;. &lt;strong&gt;It&#x27;s hard to state how much this trial revealed&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; - if you want to read more I suggest &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.theverge.com&#x2F;22611236&#x2F;epic-v-apple-emails-project-liberty-app-store-schiller-sweeney-cook-jobs&quot;&gt;this article by the Verge&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; which uncovers some points in emails brought up during the trial, and of course if you somehow have time you can read &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;storage.courtlistener.com&#x2F;recap&#x2F;gov.uscourts.cand.364265&#x2F;gov.uscourts.cand.364265.812.0_3.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;the full 185 page ruling here&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (although most press articles have summarised some main points and conclusions from that). Interestingly as well, the NSA &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;9to5mac.com&#x2F;2013&#x2F;09&#x2F;10&#x2F;nsa-references-original-macintosh-ad-in-calling-steve-jobs-big-brother-and-iphone-owners-zombies&#x2F;&quot;&gt;also made the same comparison as Epic&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; privately, although perhaps for different reasons. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-20-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, it’s easier on some Android devices than others, but definitely not near-impossible like on iOS devices. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-3-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-4&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fun fact: this is why you need to resign apps every week on newer jailbroken devices, because Apple utilises signing everywhere for software on iOS (more specifically, jailbreakers utilise development certificates to get around these signing measures, which is why they expire after a week). There are tools such as &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;cydia.akemi.ai&#x2F;?page&#x2F;net.angelxwind.appsyncunified&quot;&gt;AppSync Unified&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;altstore.io&#x2F;&quot;&gt;AltStore&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that negotiate around this in a way, but you can see it is more cumbersome than Android. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-4-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-5&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nice thing however is that even Apple can’t modify it, so jailbreak exploits from it such as the famous &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arstechnica.com&#x2F;information-technology&#x2F;2019&#x2F;09&#x2F;developer-of-checkm8-explains-why-idevice-jailbreak-exploit-is-a-game-changer&#x2F;&quot;&gt;checkm8&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; cannot be patched. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-5-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-6&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d like to point out there is &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;getutm.app&#x2F;&quot;&gt;this awesome open source virtual machine app called UTM&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that allows you to run virtual machines with OSs such as Linux distributions or even Windows itself on iOS, but unfortunately for me &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;utmapp&#x2F;UTM&#x2F;issues&#x2F;405&quot;&gt;it only supports iOS 11 and above&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, so much like older Android devices and their updates my older iPad 3 will never see it :( &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-6-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-7&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also for another thought - I wonder if you have an untethered jailbreak that perhaps you could boot into another OS from perhaps a partition on the device? It wouldn’t be perfect as you would have to boot into iOS anyway first which is annoying, but would it be possible? It feels similar to vein to asking whether it would be possible to switch execution and boot into a Linux distro while Windows is running (perhaps by killing off Windows processes). If I had more experience I would try it, but I wonder if it is possible. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-7-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-8&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest, I’m more amazed Apple somehow hasn’t taken legal action against Cydia for selling paid iOS apps and tweaks outside the App Store, given that Apple is quite willing to take legal action against companies for issues such as &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.theregister.com&#x2F;2018&#x2F;02&#x2F;13&#x2F;apple_github_iboot&#x2F;&quot;&gt;source code leaks&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.theverge.com&#x2F;2021&#x2F;8&#x2F;11&#x2F;22620014&#x2F;apple-corellium-security-virtual-iphone-dmca-lawsuit-settled&quot;&gt;iOS virtual machines&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, and Apple would certainly be aware of Cydia’s existence if not before &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.theverge.com&#x2F;2020&#x2F;12&#x2F;10&#x2F;22167964&#x2F;cydia-sues-apple-monopoly-anticompetitive-iphone&quot;&gt;by its own lawsuit against the perceived iOS monopoly&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Perhaps paid iOS “homebrew” is legal? &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-8-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-9&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe updating is possible if you are jailbroken, although you have to wait for a jailbreak for the updated iOS version if there isn’t one available (since semi-untethered jailbreaks do not survive a reboot) &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-9-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-10&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in reading more about Pegasus, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;citizenlab.ca&#x2F;tag&#x2F;pegasus&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Citizen Lab&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (who discovered it in 2016) has some excellent articles on it and the people affected. There’s also &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;OutOfTheLoop&#x2F;comments&#x2F;opzpd2&#x2F;what_is_going_on_with_pegasus_project&#x2F;h6avn1e&#x2F;&quot;&gt;this Reddit comment&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; which I found gives a nice balanced and wide overview surrounding the nature and origin of these tools. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-10-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-11&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve confused by how Google is allowed to do this, my understanding is that Android is a program that runs on top of the Linux kernel and is not combined with it - &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;torvalds&#x2F;linux&#x2F;blob&#x2F;master&#x2F;LICENSES&#x2F;exceptions&#x2F;Linux-syscall-note&quot;&gt;there’s a GPL exception in the Linux kernel for the syscall interface anyway&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. There are a lot of proprietary legal applications that run on Linux such as Steam and Microsoft Teams, so in a sense Android is legal. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-11-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-12&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some argue that the source code being public means that it is easier to find vulnerabilities in Android, but in my opinion that’s a good thing, because they can be patched quickly. The security of an operating system should never depend on its code being private - trying to do this is called “&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Security_through_obscurity&quot;&gt;security through obscurity&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;” - and it seems unanimously people agree it is a bad idea, as &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.debian.org&#x2F;security&#x2F;&quot;&gt;exemplified by open source projects such as Debian&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-12-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-13&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also see Google’s willingness to embrace third-party security researchers more readily than Apple, given that they &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;android-developers.googleblog.com&#x2F;2017&#x2F;04&#x2F;an-investigation-of-chrysaor-malware-on.html&quot;&gt;have uploaded Chrysaor binaries to VirusTotal (at the bottom of the post)&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. They even notified those who had been affected, unlike Apple. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-13-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-14&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost certainly, at least, because in a similar vein to default software repositories on Linux distributions all the applications have open source code, so they can be checked by others and built into binaries on the servers themselves. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-14-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-22&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s more amusing to me is that this all started because &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;IBM_PC_compatible&quot;&gt;everyone was cloning IBM’s PC&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, so it seems entirely accidental. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-22-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-23&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest I don’t know if it can be conjured into being, perhaps Google should strong arm OEMs into supporting UEFI. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-23-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-15&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see this isn’t good for e-waste either. Some would also say that the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Batterygate&quot;&gt;slowing down of iPhones with newer software updates&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, but at least they last for longer in theory: iOS devices seem to last around 6 years, while Android devices such as those from Google may reach 2 years if you are lucky. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-15-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-16&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess blame could be placed on OEMs for heavily customising Android for their devices (in the sense that they burden themselves to maintain their forks more rather than using features present in “mainline” Android&#x2F;the Linux kernel), but some are also &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;Android&#x2F;comments&#x2F;grlik7&#x2F;two_years_of_software_updates_is_no_longer_enough&#x2F;fs0c5gt&quot;&gt;shifting some blame onto Google&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; in the same vein. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-16-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-17&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And also if there was &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;AndroidQuestions&#x2F;comments&#x2F;mk3k3z&#x2F;why_is_android_so_locked_down_compared_to_linux&#x2F;gtdouq0?utm_source=share&amp;amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;amp;context=3&quot;&gt;some standardised BIOS&#x2F;UEFI for ARM like on PCs&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, but maybe that’s asking too much. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-17-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-18&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fun fact: given that Android uses the Linux kernel, and that the Linux kernel is licensed under GPL, in theory you can &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.xda-developers.com&#x2F;oems-and-gpl-compliance&#x2F;&quot;&gt;legally ask your Android OEM to give you the source code for the kernel&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; because they obviously distribute the kernel as part of the phone. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-18-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-21&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Funnily enough, since I brought up the Epic Games trial here, &lt;strong&gt;Tim Sweeney&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, the CEO who is leading this &quot;crusade&quot; (as Judge Rogers put it in the ruling) against Apple &lt;strong&gt;uses an iPhone himself&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; as well. &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;storage.courtlistener.com&#x2F;recap&#x2F;gov.uscourts.cand.364265&#x2F;gov.uscourts.cand.364265.812.0_3.pdf&quot;&gt;From the ruling&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;&quot;Mr. Sweeney himself owns an iPhone in part because of its better security and privacy than Android.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (on p.110) and &lt;em&gt;&quot;Mr. Sweeney, an iPhone user himself, admitted that he found Apple’s approach to privacy and customer data security superior to Google’s approach to customer privacy and customer data.&quot;&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (on p.45). It&#x27;s rather funny, and I&#x27;ve also realised from this (although it&#x27;s probably obvious) that for Apple it is more important business-wise to sell devices rather than Google (which obtains most of its revenue from advertising), which may explain why Android is in a more &quot;dire&quot; state. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-21-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-19&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, as mentioned, you can jailbreak, but as Android is more accommodating to openness in general it is considerably better in this regard, such as in terms of the amount of possible software. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-19-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Thoughts on switching to Linux (and why you could)</title>
        <published>2021-08-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2021-08-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.jamesravindran.com/blog/thoughts-on-switching-to-linux/"/>
        <id>https://www.jamesravindran.com/blog/thoughts-on-switching-to-linux/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://www.jamesravindran.com/blog/thoughts-on-switching-to-linux/">&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;tux-enhanced-v2.svg&quot; alt=&quot;Tux the penguin, mascot of Linux&quot; height=&quot;350&quot;&#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Tux_(mascot)&quot;&gt;Tux the penguin&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, mascot of Linux&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-0-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-0&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’re probably heard of &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Linux&quot;&gt;Linux&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-1-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-1&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; Here I’ll try to summarise some advantages and disadvantages, some of which I have found when switching myself to Linux Mint.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(also feel free to scroll down to the end for a quick tl;dr if you’re running a little short on time)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;advantages&quot;&gt;Advantages&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many advantages of Linux (privacy; customizability - that’s a common one; philosophical (i.e. a community effort to build an operating system and software rather than using the proprietary ones provided by a company) etc.) that I’m sure many people have said on the web (&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;linux_gaming&#x2F;comments&#x2F;7n6bc9&#x2F;switching_to_linux_is_it_worth&#x2F;drzef6x&quot;&gt;this is a good Reddit comment I found&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;), so you’re free to check those out. Two main ones that might be the most applicable:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Linux is free&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. Of course, Linux is philosophically free “as in speech” (&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.gnu.org&#x2F;philosophy&#x2F;free-sw.html&quot;&gt;as Richard Stallman phrases it&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;) being &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;GNU_General_Public_License&quot;&gt;free and open-source software under the GPL license&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, and from that it’s also free “as in beer” i.e. price. &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Linux_distribution&quot;&gt;Linux distros&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; are typically&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-2-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-2&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; free to download and install&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-3-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-3&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;, so it’s quite easy to find one and try it out. In turn, given the community around it, &lt;strong&gt;much of the software on Linux is free and open-source&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; as well.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Linux works better than Windows on older hardware&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. Have older hardware? Don’t use outdated operating systems such as Windows XP! Simply slap a Linux distro on it, and you’ll be able to keep using your computer and still receive the latest security and software updates. Of course, as I’m about to mention, it won’t be a 100% seamless transition, but for most everyday activities such as browsing the web, emailing, writing documents etc. it should be perfectly fine.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;disadvantages&quot;&gt;Disadvantages&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, Linux is, as you are probably aware, developed by a community of volunteers around the world, and although there is some commercial support from companies such as Canonical and Red Hat, it’s hard to compete with more proprietary companies who spend lots of time and money “polishing” their operating systems for mainstream usage (more specifically, the user interfaces).&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-4-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-4&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; Nonetheless, I feel it’s prudent to say Linux can’t be easily dismissed, due to its extensive community and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Linux#Commercial_and_popular_uptake&quot;&gt;much usage&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; on servers, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.zdnet.com&#x2F;article&#x2F;linux-totally-dominates-supercomputers&#x2F;&quot;&gt;supercomputers&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-5-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-5&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; and most famously Android, and it definitely is (in my opinion) 99% of the way there as a desktop distro for the mainstream (a lot of people are using it as a daily driver perfectly fine) - but if you’re considering switching, you do have to be aware there are a few rough edges.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are two I encountered (the first one being more of an issue for me at least):&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lack of HiDPI support&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. Linux desktop environments seemingly (or at least consistently) &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;linux&#x2F;comments&#x2F;n05z7k&#x2F;why_is_hidpi_support_on_linux_still_so_bad&#x2F;&quot;&gt;haven’t caught up with the high-resolution displays released&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; in the last decades or so.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-6-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-6&quot;&gt;[7]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; You can see &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;wiki.archlinux.org&#x2F;title&#x2F;HiDPI&quot;&gt;an overview on the Arch Linux wiki&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (which is famed for being a well-reputed source of Linux-related information). To my knowledge (and as of mid-2021), recent versions of GNOME, KDE Plasma, Xfce and Cinnamon (which I use on Linux Mint) should work okay, but DEs like MATE, Pantheon, Enlightenment etc. may need some more workarounds.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, even if the desktop environment does attempt to support it, desktop applications on Linux can use different application frameworks (such as GTK, QT etc.), so you may have to manually pass environment variables (&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;obsproject.com&#x2F;forum&#x2F;threads&#x2F;font-scaling-in-the-obs-ui.110176&#x2F;post-498812&quot;&gt;here’s a random example for OBS Studio&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;) and other fixes to get them to scale correctly, and even then it may be slightly buggy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Less software support&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. Of course, most developers (particularly commercial ones) only make software (such as video games, video editing software, music production software, Outlook etc.) for Windows, so you’ll have to find alternatives that run on Linux.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although there are tools such as Wine, Lutris, PlayOnLinux etc.,&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-7-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-7&quot;&gt;[8]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;steamcommunity.com&#x2F;games&#x2F;221410&#x2F;announcements&#x2F;detail&#x2F;1696055855739350561&quot;&gt;Valve particularly is pushing development on its own fork of Wine called Proton&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; so most of your &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Steam_(service)&quot;&gt;Steam&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; video games can be run out-of-the-box, if you run Windows software using these tools you can encounter performance issues and bugs, so it is always preferable to find native Linux versions, which (although subjective) you might find inferior.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s worthwhile however to point out there is a lot of high-quality and respected open source software equivalents (which you might prefer to use even on Windows compared to their proprietary equivalents), such as &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.videolan.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;VLC Player&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.libreoffice.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;LibreOffice&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.gimp.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;GIMP&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;handbrake.fr&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Handbrake&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, the amazing &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.blender.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Blender&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; etc. so I’m sure you’ll find something (or a workaround at least).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, which Linux distro to choose? Well, it’s up to you, but &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;FindMeADistro&#x2F;comments&#x2F;5sg4f7&#x2F;how_to_select_a_distro&#x2F;&quot;&gt;I highly recommend you read this guide I found on the Reddit subreddit “FindMeADistro&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;”. It very clearly goes through the crucial differences between different distros, and gives a few use cases at the end that you may be able to apply to yourself.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you’re a complete beginner and you’re not really sure&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-8-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-8&quot;&gt;[9]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;, I’d recommend &lt;strong&gt;a Ubuntu-based distro&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; would probably be a good choice. I personally recommend &lt;strong&gt;Linux Mint&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (which I use) because:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has &lt;strong&gt;a Windows-like interface&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, the Cinnamon desktop environment (I mean, you could probably get used to it, but I feel GNOME 3 may be initially confusing for a beginner).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a &lt;strong&gt;Ubuntu-based distro&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, so you get all the advantages from that (convenience&#x2F;being usable out-of-the-box, solutions on the web for Ubuntu will probably work with Linux Mint).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;strong&gt;lots of easy-to-use GUI tools in Linux Mint&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, such as the Update Manager, Driver Manager etc. so this nicely hand-holds you into the world of Linux and therefore &lt;strong&gt;you don’t need to touch the terminal at all on a day-to-day basis&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (personally I don’t find the terminal - being an aspiring programmer - that scary at all, but these tools will probably let you avoid using it completely&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-9-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-9&quot;&gt;[10]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s &lt;strong&gt;plenty of beginner-friendly help around on the Linux Mint forums&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; - particularly this &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;forums.linuxmint.com&#x2F;viewforum.php?f=90&quot;&gt;beginner section&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; - so feel free to ask there if there’s a problem or you’re unsure about how to do something.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;arch-linux&quot;&gt;Arch Linux?&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d like to say first I don’t want to trigger any Arch Linux fans out, but given that it is notably famous, I will mention I personally &lt;strong&gt;wouldn’t recommend it for beginners&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (and to be honest - as someone who’s quite busy as a student - even myself), because:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arch Linux &lt;strong&gt;heavily focuses on customizability&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. There is no easy installer as on Ubuntu or Debian - everything, from partitioning the disks to setting up the desktop environment, has to be done on the initial command-line terminal. If you &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;wiki.archlinux.org&#x2F;title&#x2F;Installation_guide&quot;&gt;follow the wiki&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; you’ll probably be able to set up fine, but if you’re expecting an out-of-the-box distro you might be quite frustrated.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arch Linux is a &lt;strong&gt;rolling release distro&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. I’ll probably do a longer post about it later, but in a nutshell it means software from the repositories is served straight from the authors i.e. upstream (unlike distros such as Debian and Ubuntu which freeze the software, pass it through several stage of testing, and then only apply security patches and (very) minor bug fixes once released). This means you will get the latest software and hardware support&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-10-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-10&quot;&gt;[11]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;, but also the latest bugs, crashes and other random changes. Then again, it’s not definite that you will experience any of this, but it is more likely.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I’m not saying it’s something that doesn’t have its merits&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (for instance, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Steam_Deck&quot;&gt;Valve chose it to build on for SteamOS 3.0 for the upcoming Steam Deck&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, likely due to its emphasis on customizability and faster updates for drivers etc.) &lt;strong&gt;and as with all Linux distros&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, if you have a decent amount of time (and perhaps a spare machine or &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.howtogeek.com&#x2F;196060&#x2F;beginner-geek-how-to-create-and-use-virtual-machines&#x2F;&quot;&gt;a virtual one&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;), you can check it out if you’re curious.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, feel free to have a read around (particularly &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;FindMeADistro&#x2F;comments&#x2F;5sg4f7&#x2F;how_to_select_a_distro&#x2F;&quot;&gt;recommending that guide I mentioned earlier&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;) and choose which distro + desktop environment (DE) you like the look of in general and that you feel aligned with its philosophy&#x2F;release cycle&#x2F;community best.&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-11-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-11&quot;&gt;[12]&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I’d like to point out one last thing - &lt;strong&gt;I recommend you keep Windows around at the side&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; as a kind of “lifeboat” (I still do this myself). You can do this through methods such as &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.howtogeek.com&#x2F;214571&#x2F;how-to-dual-boot-linux-on-your-pc&#x2F;&quot;&gt;dual-booting&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.howtogeek.com&#x2F;196060&#x2F;beginner-geek-how-to-create-and-use-virtual-machines&#x2F;&quot;&gt;running Linux in a virtual machine&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; or using Linux on a second device. One thing is that you might not like Linux and prefer Windows (which is fine - use whatever you like), but most importantly I think (from experience) that trying to 100% migrate everything that you may do on Windows daily wouldn’t be instantaneous (you’ll have to find equivalent software, maybe find workarounds for bugs or other requirements etc.). &lt;strong&gt;This is particularly important to note if you need to use your computer for important daily work&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (e.g. you have to attend frequent virtual work&#x2F;school&#x2F;university meetings&#x2F;lessons). But it might be a nice thing to try out Linux when you have time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tl-dr&quot;&gt;tl:dr;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to try out Linux as a beginner:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;FindMeADistro&#x2F;comments&#x2F;5sg4f7&#x2F;how_to_select_a_distro&#x2F;&quot;&gt;this guide&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for a good comparison&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; between the distros.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you’re not sure, consider choosing a &lt;strong&gt;Ubuntu-based distro&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (I recommend &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;linuxmint.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Linux Mint&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;).&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep Windows around in case&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; you don’t like a distro and&#x2F;or need to row back (especially if you’ve got important daily work you need to do).&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-0&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.gnome-look.org&#x2F;p&#x2F;1102260&quot;&gt;&quot;Tux Enhanced&quot;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; by Frank Souza (licensed under &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;creativecommons.org&#x2F;licenses&#x2F;by&#x2F;2.0&#x2F;&quot;&gt;CC BY 2.0&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;) &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-0-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mean, there are obviously a large number of resources etc. surrounding Linux, but I found the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=o8NPllzkFhE&quot;&gt;TED talk from the man himself&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; really gives a nice overview of how it fits into the bigger picture. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-1-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some such as &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.redhat.com&#x2F;en&#x2F;technologies&#x2F;linux-platforms&#x2F;enterprise-linux&quot;&gt;Red Hat Enterprise Linux&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that require a commercial license - although even that has become &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arstechnica.com&#x2F;gadgets&#x2F;2021&#x2F;01&#x2F;centos-is-gone-but-rhel-is-now-free-for-up-to-16-production-servers&#x2F;&quot;&gt;free now because of backlash against the discontinuation of CentOS&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-2-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, downloading it in the first place and writing it to a USB&#x2F;CD may require you to have a computer with another OS installed, but given most OEM laptops have Windows installed as part of the price, you probably have one around. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-3-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-4&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And of course, these companies typically associated with more proprietary operating systems and software have also embraced open source in some respects, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource.google&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Google&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource.microsoft.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Microsoft&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource.apple.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Apple&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;opensource.fb.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; etc. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-4-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-5&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even Microsoft uses Ubuntu on its four supercomputers! &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-5-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-6&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest, even companies that make proprietary OSs struggle with this as well apparently. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-6-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-7&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be clear, the latter ones all use Wine (or are compatible with forks such as Proton), but they make it much easier to use Wine which can be quite difficult to configure. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-7-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-8&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, if the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;upload.wikimedia.org&#x2F;wikipedia&#x2F;commons&#x2F;8&#x2F;8c&#x2F;Linux_Distribution_Timeline_Dec._2020.svg&quot;&gt;amount of choice available&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is causing you to &quot;distro-hop&quot;, I recommend watching &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=3zpgQpdy_fI&quot;&gt;this video&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. You don’t have to watch it all (I only watched the first few minutes) but the critical parts in my opinion are roughy 1:52 to 2:09, and 2:51 to 3:20 - it basically says you &lt;strong&gt;don’t need the find the &quot;best&quot; distro&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (because it doesn’t exist), you just &lt;strong&gt;need one to get the job done (i.e. your day-to-day work)&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. If there is a big problem that you can’t work around &lt;strong&gt;then you can switch&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, but &lt;strong&gt;otherwise stick with the one you currently got.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-8-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-9&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mean there might be a problem that does require you to use it, but I’m sure the people on the Linux Mint forums will guide you through it, and Linux Mint is pretty stable so you’re unlikely to encounter them. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-9-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-10&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note it’s not as black-and-white. Ubuntu realised this newer hardware support problem and provides &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;askubuntu.com&#x2F;questions&#x2F;248914&#x2F;what-is-hardware-enablement-hwe&quot;&gt;a newer kernel via what they call the &quot;Hardware Enablement Stack&quot;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (and I guess you could try to drop one in yourself in any stable distro anyway) and newer software can be brought in on a stable distro via &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;backports.debian.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;backports&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; or through new technologies such as &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;appimage.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;AppImages&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;flathub.org&quot;&gt;FlatHub&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;snapcraft.io&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Snaps&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;linux&#x2F;comments&#x2F;j3ajnf&#x2F;whats_wrong_with_snaps_why_so_many_people_hate_it&quot;&gt;although the last is controversial&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;). &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-10-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-11&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know on most distros other DEs than the default can be installed later, but some distros will work with and look better with certain DEs (e.g. Cinnamon is heavily customised for Linux Mint), and switching will probably be inconvenient as configuration files that multiple DEs might share would interface with each other. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-11-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
